Guide to the Edgar Marquess Branch Papers, 1939-2003 and undated RL.00144
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Edgar Marquess Branch papers
1939-2003 and undated (bulk 1960-1990)
1960-1990
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Branch, Edgar Marquess, 1913-
RL.00144
10 Linear Feet
4052 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Edgar Marquess Branch Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts from 1981 through 2004.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1913 Mar. 21 Born in Chicago, Ill., son of Raymond Sydney (publisher) and Marian (Marquess) Branch
1932-1933 Studied at University College, London
1934 Received A.B. from Beloit College, Beloit, Wis.
1934-1935 Graduate study at Brown University
1938 Received M.A. from the University of Chicago
1939, Apr. 29 Married Mary Josephine (Mary Jo) Emerson
1941 Received Ph.D. in English from the University of Iowa
1941-1943 Instructor at Miami University, Oxford, Ohio
1942 (Editor) Mark Twain's Letters in the Muscatine Journal
1943-1949 Assistant Professor of English at Miami University, Oxford, Ohio
1949 Visiting Associate Professor at the University of Missouri, Columbia, Mo.
1949-1957 Associate Professor of English at Miami University
1950 Published The Literary Apprenticeship of Mark Twain
1957-1964 Professor of English at Miami University, and Chair of the English Department from 1959-1964
1959 Published A Bibliography of James T. Farrell's Writings, 1921-1957
1964-1968 Research Professor of English at Miami University
1969 (Editor and author of the introduction and preface) Clemens of the Call
1971 Published James T. Farrell
1972 Published (with Frederick Anderson) The Great Landslide Case
1975 Named literary executor of the James T. Farrell estate
1978 Named Research Professor of English Emeritus and Research Associate in American Literature at Miami University
1979 Editor, with Robert H. Hirst, and with the assistance of Harriet Elinor Smith, of Mark Twain, Early Tales and Sketches, Volume 1: 1851-1864
1980-1990 Member of the Board of Directors of the Mark Twain Project in Berkeley, Calif.
1981 Mark Twain, Early Tales and Sketches, Volume 2: 1864-1865
1985 (With Robert H. Hirst) The Grangerford-Shepherdson Feud: Life and Death at Compromise, Friends of the Bancroft Library, University of California Press (Berkeley, Calif.).
1985 Published Men Call Me Lucky: Mark Twain and the "Pennsylvania"
1988-1997 Editor, with Michael B. Frank and Kenneth M. Sanderson, Mark Twain's Letters, Volume 1: 1853-1866, Volume 2: 1867-1868, Volume 5: 1872-1873
1992 Published Mark Twain and the Starchy Boys
1993 Editor, with H.E. Smith, Roughing It
1996 Published Studs Lonigan's Neighborhood and the Making of James T. Farrell
1998 Published A Paris Year: Dorothy and James T. Farrell, 1931-1932
Collection Overview
The Edgar Marquess Branch Papers span the years from 1939 to 2003, with the majority of the materials dating from 1960 to 1990. Through correspondence and writings, they document Branch's lifelong research on nineteenth-century American author Mark Twain. Important correspondents include such Twain scholars as Fred Anderson, Louis Budd, Cyril Clemens, Robert Hirst, and Henry Nash Smith. Topics chiefly focus on issues concerning academic writers, and Twain's life and literary output. Although the bulk of this collection concerns Branch's work on Twain, it should be noted that Professor Branch was also an eminent scholar of James T. Farrell, a twentieth-century American novelist best known for his "Studs Lonigan" series (1932-1935). Branch's papers are organized into three series: Correspondence, Special Projects Files, and Writings. Although Branch taught for many years as a Professor of English, there are no teaching materials in the collection. However, the correspondence may contain some references to teaching American literature and to activities as a faculty member at Miami University in Oxford, Ohio.
The Correspondence Series, the largest series in the collection, is organized into two subseries. The Individuals Subseries documents Branch's contacts over many decades with numerous Twain scholars, literary critics, and former students. There are also letters concerning his contacts with institutions such as the Mark Twain Boyhood Home Association. The Journals and Publishers Subseries contains Branch's correspondence with many well-known publishing firms and academic presses. Most of the correspondence is routine in nature but attests to Branch's lengthy and prolific writing career. In a few cases, drafts of writings are attached to his correspondence.
The bulk of the Mark Twain Special Projects Files Series consists of documents that pertain to Branch's service on the Board of Directors for the Mark Twain Project, based at the University of California at Berkeley, from 1980 to 1990. Administrative files and grant application files make up the majority of the materials.
The Writings Series consists of manuscripts and galley proofs of the Early Tales and Sketches of Mark Twain, Volume 1, and the page proofs for Early Tales and Sketches, Volume 2. Branch co-edited both of these volumes, which were published in 1979 and 1981, respectively.
Galley proofs; Scholars -- Correspondence; College teachers as authors; Authors and publishers -- United States -- Correspondence; Scholars -- United States -- Correspondence; Literary historians -- United States; American literature -- Southern States -- History and criticism; American literature -- Study and teaching; Mark Twain Project; Branch, Edgar Marquess, 1913-; Budd, Louis J.; Anderson, Frederick, 1926-; Hirst, Robert H.; Miami University (Oxford, Ohio) -- Faculty; Clemens, Cyril, 1902-; Farrell, James T. (James Thomas), 1904-1979; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910; Smith, Henry Nash
- Correspondence Series, 1939-2003 and undated, bulk 1960-1990
  Scope and Contents note
  Organized into two subseries: Individuals, and Journals and Publishers.
  - Individuals Subseries, 1939-2003 and undated
    Branch's correspondents include many eminent Twain scholars such as Fred Anderson, Minnie M. Brashear, George H. Brownell, Louis J. Budd, Cyril Clemens (who was also a second cousin of Twain's), Hennig Cohen, Everett Emerson, Paul Fatout, Alan Gribben, Hamlin Hill, Robert Hirst, and Henry Nash Smith. Other correspondents of note include literary critics Matthew J. Bruccoli, John Crowe Ransom, Arlin Turner, and René Wellek; as well as Ira Berkow (NY Times sportswriter/journalist and former student of Branch's) and W. Willard Wirtz (former U.S. Secretary of Labor under Presidents John F. Kennedy and Lyndon B. Johnson). Arranged alphabetically by last name of the correspondent.
    - Adkins, Nelson F., 1946 (Box 1)
    - Akao, Ken'ichi, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Allen, Charles, 1952-1957 (Box 1)
    - Anderson, Fred, 1963-1979 (Box 1)
    - Armon, Dahlia, 1985-1989 (Box 1)
    - Armstrong, Robert, 1983-1986 (Box 1)
    - Atkins, Carol, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Baender, Paul, 1964-1983 (Box 1)
    - Baetzhold, Howard, 1965-1992, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Baker, William, 1977-1999 (Box 1)
    - Barnes, Warner, 1964-1966 (Box 1)
    - Bartenhagen, Mabel, 1941 (Box 1)
    - Baskin, Darryl, 1988-1992 (Box 1)
    - Bates, Allan, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Bebb, Bruce, 1975-1978 (Box 1)
    - Beckett, William, 1965-1974 (Box 1)
    - Berkove, Lawrence, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
    - Berkow, Ira, 1969-1988 (Box 1)
    - Blair, Walter, 1956-1986 (Box 1)
    - Bochynski, Kevin J., 1998-2000 (Box 1)
    - Brack, O.M., Jr., 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Brashear, Minnie M., 1940 (Box 1)
    - Bredwell, Martha, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - Bridgman, Richard, 1977-1986 (Box 1)
    - Brinegar, Claude S., 1963 (Box 1)
    - Britton, Wesley, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Brown, David, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Brown, Donald J., 1985 (Box 1)
    - Brown, Harry, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Browne, Ray B., 1967 (Box 1)
    - Brownell, George H., 1939-1950 (Box 1)
    - Browning, Robert P., 1990 (Box 1)
    - Bruccoli, Matthew J., 1963-1973 (Box 1)
    - Bucci, Rick, 1986-1993 (Box 1)
    - Buchanan, Buck, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Buckler, Patricia, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Budd, Louis J., 1963-1997, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Butterfield, Roger, 1965-1970 (Box 2)
    - Carroll, William, 1981-1995 (Box 2)
    - Carter, Edward T., 1949 (Box 2)
    - Carter, Paul, 1948-1968 (Box 2)
    - Casciato, Arthur, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Chamberlain, Thomas G., 1949 (Box 2)
    - Cho, Sungkyu, 1980-1990 (Box 2)
    - Clemens, Cyril, 1943-1980 (Box 2)
    - Cohen, Hennig, 1962-1979 (Box 2)
    - Connor, Ralph, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Cornman, Charles, 1963-1967 (Box 2)
    - Covici, Pascal, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Cox, James, 1953-1992 (Box 2)
    - Cummings, Sherwood, 1962, 1986-1990 (Box 2)
    - Cushman, Bigelow Paine, 1966-1979 (Box 2)
    - Dahl, Curtis, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Daloney, Thomas Ewing, 1945 (Box 2)
    - David, Beverly, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Davis, Chester, 1950-1979 (Box 2)
    - Dee, Rich, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Dempsey, Terrell D., 2001-2002 (Box 2)
    - DeVoto, Bernard, 1941-1949 (Box 2)
    - Dickinson, Leon, 1949-1967 (Box 2)
    - Dickson, William C., 1974 (Box 2)
    - Doyno, Victor, 1992, 2001, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Duerksen, Roland, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Duskis, Henry, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Emerson, Everett, 1978-1987 (Box 2)
    - Engle, Gary, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Fanning, Philip, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Fatout, Paul, 1963-1983 (Box 2)
    - Ferris, Ruth, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Fischer, Victor, 1979-1989 (Box 2)
    - Frank, Michael, 1973-1994 (Box 2)
    - Frear, Walter, 1942-1949 (Box 2)
    - Fried, Martin, 1963-1969 (Box 2)
    - Fritz, Donald W., 1979 (Box 2)
    - Gale, Robert L., 1972-1979 (Box 2)
    - Gerber, John, 1962-1984 (Box 2)
    - Gibson, William, 1966-1983 (Box 2)
    - Gilreath, James, 1991-1994 (Box 2)
    - Gordon, Laura and Dale Kutnick, 1987 (Box 2)
    - Graves, Roy, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Gregory, Ralph, 1966-1979 (Box 2)
    - Gribben, Alan, 1968-1995 (Box 2)
    - Hall, James, 1950 (Box 2)
    - Hammond, George C., 1985 (Box 2)
    - Hanff, Peter E., 1993 (Box 2)
    - Hanger, Bill, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Hart, James D., 1979-1987 (Box 2)
    - Havighurst, Walter, 1969-1983 (Box 2)
    - Hayford, Harrison, 1946 (Box 2)
    - Heimbeck, A. Willard, Rev., 1976-1978 (Box 2)
    - Henderson, Archibald, 1949 (Box 2)
    - Henderson, Roswell P., 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - Henneberger, Mary K., 1979 (Box 2)
    - Hermann, Ruth, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Hill, Hamlin, 1965-1979 (Box 2)
    - Hillyer, Katherine, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Hirst, Robert H., 1972-2003 and undated, 10 folders (Box 3)
    - Hoeltje, H.H., 1950-1968 (Box 3)
    - Hoffman, Andrew J., 1993-1994 (Box 3)
    - Hoffman, Daniel G., 1951 (Box 4)
    - Holmes, William, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Holte, Carlton, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Hornberger, Theodore, 1942 (Box 4)
    - Howells, Mildred, 1948-1949 (Box 4)
    - Husted, Wayne, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Johnson, Bob, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Johnson, Haynes, 1986 (Box 4)
    - Johnson, Walter J., 1964 (Box 4)
    - Joyce, Richard, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Kahn, Solomon J., 1986 (Box 4)
    - Kaplan, Adam, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Kaplan, Justin, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Karanovich, Nick, 1986-1995 (Box 4)
    - Keeter, Robert, 1969-1980 (Box 4)
    - Kemble, John H., 1965 (Box 4)
    - Keniston, Maxwell R., 1989 (Box 4)
    - Kennedy, Susan, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Ketterer, David, 1980-1985 (Box 4)
    - Kiskis, Michael, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Klinger, Eric von, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
    - Kobylka, Joseph, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Krause, Sydney, 1964-1989 (Box 4)
    - Kruse, Horst H., 1992-1993 (Box 4)
    - Laidlaw, Arrianne, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Lauber, John, 1980-1985 (Box 4)
    - Laurence, Michael, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Leisy, Ernest E., 1941-1955 (Box 4)
    - Leary, Lewis, 1965 (Box 4)
    - LeMaster, J. R., 1995 (Box 4)
    - Leonard, James, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Lewis, Oscar, 1945 (Box 4)
    - Lillard, Richard G., 1941-1950 (Box 4)
    - Long, E. Hudson, 1947-1969 (Box 4)
    - Lorch, Fred W., 1945-1950 (Box 4)
    - MacDonnell, Kevin, 2000-2002 (Box 4)
    - Machlis, Paul, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Mack, Effie Mona, 1948 (Box 4)
    - Mann, David, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Mann, Roy B., 2002 Mar. 13 (Box 4)
    - Marchand, Roland, 1986 (Box 4)
    - Marleau, Michael, 1978-1996, 2000-2002 and undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Marovitz, Sanford E., 1979-1992 (Box 4)
    - Martin, John H., 1993 (Box 4)
    - McCarthy, Jack, 1966 (Box 4)
    - McClain, Laurence, 1987 (Box 4)
    - McClung, William J., 1986 (Box 4)
    - McCullough, Joseph, 1968-1972 (Box 4)
    - McDonald, Russell W., 1971-1972 (Box 4)
    - McGrath, Roger, 1986 (Box 4)
    - McKinsey, Elizabeth R., 1986 (Box 4)
    - McNutt, James C., 1977-1981 (Box 4)
    - Meine, Franklin, 1940-1969 (Box 4)
    - Meltzer, Milton, 1966-1970 (Box 4)
    - Miller, Edwin H., 1992 (Box 4)
    - Miller, Richard G., 1971 (Box 4)
    - Miller, Mrs. Robert A., 1969 (Box 4)
    - Miller, William, 1971-1985 (Box 4)
    - Morgan, Hugh, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Moran, Irene, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Morris, Evans, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Morris, Irma Wright, undated (Box 4)
    - Neider, Charles, 1965-1979 (Box 4)
    - Nelson, Malcolm, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
    - Newgarden, Albert, 1993 (Box 5)
    - Nickerson, Thomas, 1948 (Box 5)
    - Noel, Tom, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Nordloh, David J., 1979 (Box 5)
    - Norton, Charles A., 1975-1993 (Box 5)
    - Nunes, Cassiano, 1948-1950, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Olsen, Howard J., 1995 (Box 5)
    - Paher, Stanley W., 1972 (Box 5)
    - Panhurst, John William, Jr., 1978-1986 (Box 5)
    - Parham, Herbert S., 1992-2002 (Box 5)
    - Parman, Michael, 1968 (Box 5)
    - Pearson, Paul G., 1986 (Box 5)
    - Peterson, Spiro, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Phelps, Henry C., 1977 (Box 5)
    - Pickett, Calder, 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - Pope, James N., 1971 (Box 5)
    - Powell, Kerry, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Quirk, Tom, 1994 (Box 5)
    - Rader, Ralph, 1978 (Box 5)
    - Ransom, John Crowe, 1947 (Box 5)
    - Ratay, Myra Sauer, 1974 (Box 5)
    - Raymer, Lawrence, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Reed, John Q., 1976 (Box 5)
    - Reed, Kenneth T., 1979, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Regan, Robert, 1970-1982 (Box 5)
    - Robinson, Forrest G., 1977-1980 (Box 5)
    - Root, Jill, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
    - Rosen, Michael, 1984-1985 (Box 5)
    - Rust, Richard D., 1966 (Box 5)
    - Rutter, Joseph W., 1993-1994 (Box 5)
    - Salamo, Lin, 1977-1991 (Box 5)
    - Salsbury, Edith Colgate, 1965-1969 (Box 5)
    - Sanderson, Kenneth, 1989-1991 (Box 5)
    - Sattelmaster, Robert, 1986-1990 (Box 5)
    - Schildgen, Robert, 1974 (Box 5)
    - Schmidt, Barbara, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Schmidt, Lillian I., 1987 (Box 5)
    - Scott, Arthur, 1952-1970 (Box 5)
    - Sessions, Judith, 1988 (Box 5)
    - Sharlow, Gretchen, 1993-1997 (Box 5)
    - Shriver, Phillip, 1970-1980 (Box 5)
    - Skandera, Laura, 1989-1992 (Box 5)
    - Sloane, David, 1979-1998 (Box 5)
    - Slotta, Robert, 2000-2002 and undated (Box 5)
    - Smith, Dwight, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Smith, Harriet, 1978-1993 (Box 5)
    - Smith, Henry Nash, 1954-1986 (Box 5)
    - Smith, Janet, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Smith, Patricia, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Standish, David, 1968-1969 (Box 5)
    - Steiner, George, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
    - Stewart, Robert E., 1975-1990 (Box 5)
    - Stone, Edward, 1960-1969 (Box 5)
    - Stronks, James B., 1950, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Stuckey, Norman, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Sutton, Richard L., Jr., 1970-1974 (Box 5)
    - Sweets, Henry, 1982-2003, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Swift, James V., 1985-1991 (Box 5)
    - Talbot, William, 1982, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Tappan, Thomas E., 1981 (Box 5)
    - Tenney, Thomas, 1978-2000, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Thomson, David, 1983 (Box 6)
    - Tippitt, Capt. William H., 1982-1993 (Box 6)
    - Todd, William B., 1969, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Tuckey, John, 1969-1987 (Box 6)
    - Turner, Arlin, 1965-1973 (Box 6)
    - Unger, Richard, 1967 (Box 6)
    - Vaughan, Louise C., 1985-1986 (Box 6)
    - Vincent, Howard, 1966-1967 (Box 6)
    - Wagenknecht, Edward, 1949-1950, 1979 (Box 6)
    - Walker, Franklin, 1940-1968 (Box 6)
    - Warfel, Harry, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
    - Way, Capt. Frederick, 1985-1990 (Box 6)
    - Weatherly, Edward H., 1950 (Box 6)
    - Webster, Samuel C., 1946-1950 (Box 6)
    - Wecter, Dixon, 1948-1950 (Box 6)
    - Wellek, René, 1950 (Box 6)
    - West, Ray B., 1950 (Box 6)
    - Westlake, Neda M., 1963, 1977 (Box 6)
    - Williamson, C.K., 1984 (Box 6)
    - Wilson, James D., 1989-1991 (Box 6)
    - Winkler, John, undated (Box 6)
    - Wirtz, W. Willard, 1986 (Box 6)
    - Wykes, David, 1964-1966 (Box 6)
  - Journals and Publishers Subseries, 1940-1990
    Contains Branch's routine correspondence with various academic journals and publishing firms. Most of the letters pertain to either Branch seeking permission to use a quote, or submitting his work for publication. In a few of the latter instances, some of Branch's article manuscripts (including his oft-reprinted essay comparing Twain's Huck Finn and Salinger's Catcher in the Rye) are attached or enclosed with his correspondence. This section is arranged alphabetically by the name of the journal or publisher.
    - American Book Company, 1948-1968 (Box 6)
    - American Folklore Society, 1951 (Box 6)
    - American Heritage, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
    - American Literary Realism, 1975-1986 (Box 6)
    - American Literature, 1942-1949 (1 of 2 folders) (Box 6)
    - American Literature, 1964-1985 (2 of 2 folders) (Box 7)
    - American Literature Abstracts, 1967-1970 (Box 7)
    - American Literature – Modern Language Association, 1948-1975 (Box 7)
    - American Quarterly, 1956-1967 (Box 7)
    - American Studies, 1974-1984 (Box 7)
    - Appleton-Century-Crofts, Inc., 1948 (Box 7)
    - Bancroft Library – University of California, 1940-1973 (Box 7)
    - Bobbs-Merrill Co., 1947-1948 (Box 7)
    - California State Historical Society Quarterly, 1965-1968 (Box 7)
    - California Press, University of, 1965-1984, 6 folders (Box 7)
    - Catholic Messenger, 1966 (Box 7)
    - Cincinnati Graduate School, University of, 1948-1949 (Box 7)
    - College English, 1947-1952 (Box 7)
    - D.C. Heath and Co., 1962-1964 (Box 7)
    - Dodd, Mead and Co., 1946-1950 (Box 7)
    - Doubleday and Co., 1947 (Box 7)
    - E.P. Dutton and Co., 1948-1949 (Box 8)
    - Fields, George (Publisher), 1948 (Box 8)
    - Friends of the Bancroft Library, 1972-1977, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Harcourt, Brace and Co., 1948-1949 (Box 8)
    - Harper and Brothers, 1947-1965 (Box 8)
    - Harper's Magazine, 1955 (Box 8)
    - Harvard University Press, 1948 (Box 8)
    - Houghton Mifflin, 1962 (Box 8)
    - Huntington Library Quarterly, 1966-1969, 1984 (Box 8)
    - Illinois Press, University of, 1948-1974, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Indiana University Press, 1969 (Box 8)
    - Iowa, State Historical Society of, 1948 (Box 8)
    - Iowa Graduate College, University of, 1948-1949 (Box 8)
    - Journal of the West, 1984 (Box 8)
    - Kenyon Review, 1947 (Box 8)
    - Knopf, Alfred A., Inc., 1948 (Box 8)
    - Lippincott, J.B. Co., 1948-1949 (Box 8)
    - Little, Brown and Co., 1948 (Box 8)
    - Longmans, Green and Co., 1948 (Box 8)
    - Mad River Review, 1966-1968 (Box 8)
    - Mark Twain Journal, 1979-1982 (Box 8)
    - Merrill, Charles E. Publishing Co., 1968 (Box 8)
    - Missouri Press, University of, 1975-1982 (Box 8)
    - Modern Language Association, 1948-1949, 1978-1980 (Box 8)
    - Modern Language Notes, 1960-1961 (Box 8)
    - Mud Island, Mississippi River Museum, 1983 (Box 8)
    - Nevada Historical Society Quarterly, 1984-1986 (Box 8)
    - New York University Press, 1970 (Box 8)
    - Nineteenth-Century Fiction, 1972, 1982-1983, 1989-1990 (Box 8)
    - North Carolina Press, University of, 1948 (Box 8)
    - Norton and Co., 1961 (Box 8)
    - Odyssey Press, 1962-1963 (Box 8)
    - Oklahoma Press, University of, 1948 (Box 8)
    - Pellegrini and Cudahy, 1947 (Box 8)
    - Pennsylvania Press, University of, 1977 (Box 8)
    - PMLA, 1966-1984 (Box 8)
    - Russell and Russell, 1966 (Box 8)
    - Salt Lake City Commercial Club, 1948 (Box 8)
    - Scott, Foresman and Company, 1962-1970 (Box 8)
    - Scribner's (Charles Scribner's and Sons), 1948 (Box 8)
    - Sewanee Review, 1947 (Box 8)
    - Southwest Review, 1949 (Box 8)
    - Stanford University Press, 1948 (Box 8)
    - Studies in American Fiction, 1983 (Box 8)
    - Studies in American Humor, 1982-1985 (Box 8)
    - United States Information Agency (USIA), 1975 (Box 8)
    - Virginia Quarterly Review, 1947, 1955 (Box 8)
    - Virginia Library, University of, 1984 (Box 8)
    - Wadsworth Publishing Co., 1967 (Box 8)
    - Western American Literature, 1975-1976, 1984 (Box 8)
    - Western Review, 1947 (Box 8)
    - Yale University Press, 1949 (Box 8)
- Mark Twain Special Projects Files Series, 1964-1996, bulk 1980-1990
  Houses documents pertaining to the administration and governance of the Mark Twain Project, based at the University of California at Berkeley. One of the objectives of the Mark Twain Project is to publish definitive and scholarly editions of Twain's writings, including material that has hitherto remained unpublished. To this end, Branch spent several summers and sabbaticals working at the Bancroft Library at UC Berkeley, where the vast majority of Mark Twain's papers are held, working on such editions as Early Tales and Sketches, Volumes 1 and 2 and Roughing It. The bulk of the documents in this series pertain to Branch's service on the Board of Directors for the Mark Twain Project from 1980 to 1990. In particular, there are several National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) grant applications included in this series. There are also folders of materials that concern a controversy arising over editorial and procedural policies of the Mark Twain Project. Arranged in chronological order.
  - 1964, Harper-Row Edition of Mark Twain (Box 9)
  - 1974-1991, Mark Twain Project Board, 6 folders (Box 9)
  - 1980-1984, 1986-1989 Mark Twain Project NEH Grant Applications, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - 1983, Robert Hirst's documents for discussion with U.C. Press (Box 9)
  - 1984-1985, Mark Twain Project controversy, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - 1986, Mark Twain Project Interim Report to NEH (Box 10)
  - 1986, Mark Twain Project NEH Final Performance Report (Box 10)
  - 1987, NEH – Robert Hirst Correspondence (Box 10)
  - 1988-1990, Mark Twain Project NEH Grant Application (Box 10)
  - 1989, Mark Twain Project NEH Final Performance Report (Box 10)
  - 1990-1996, Mark Twain Project NEH Grant Application, 3 folders (Box 10)
- Writings Series, 1977-1980
  Consists of manuscripts and galley proofs of the Early Tales and Sketches (ET+S) of Mark Twain, Volume 1, and the page proofs for Early Tales and Sketches, Volume 2. Branch co-edited both of these volumes, which were published in 1979 and 1981, respectively. The galley proofs of ET+S Volume 1 and the page proofs of ET+S Volume 2 are oversized materials. Arranged in original order.
  - Manuscript: Early Tales and Sketches of Mark Twain, Vol. 1, 1977-1980 (Box 10)
    - Historical Introduction (Box 10)
    - Textual Introduction, pp. 1-152, 2 folders (Box 10)
      (153 ff lacking)
  - Manuscript: Early Tales and Sketches of Mark Twain, Vol. 1, 1977-1980 (Box 11)
    - Footnotes to Textual Introduction and Description of Texts (Box 11)
    - Tales, 1-71, 6 folders (Box 11)
    - Appendix A, C and Index (Box 11)
- Oversize Materials
  - Writings Series, 1977-1980 (Box 12-13)
    - Galley proofs: Early Tales and Sketches of Mark Twain, Vol. 1, 1977-1980
      - Introductory Material (Box 12)
      - Pages 1-197, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Page proofs: Early Tales and Sketches of Mark Twain, Vol. 2, 1977-1980
      - Pages 1-516, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Notes (Box 13)